<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://womanonrails.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://womanonrails.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2020-03-23T14:27:46-04:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Woman on Rails</title><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">TDD - Basics</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/tdd-basic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TDD - Basics" /><published>2020-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/tdd-basic</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="tdd" /><category term="tests" /><summary type="html">When it comes to programming I always think about the quality. And when we talk about quality, we need to mention testing. Testing software is very important. This is for me so natural, so transparent that almost obvious. I realized that this isn’t obvious to everyone on one of my presentations. I asked the audience about testing and I have already known, that I need to talk about testing more. When I write a code, I also write tests, but I do that in reverse order. First, I write a test, then the code. This are for me two elements in one process - software development. You can see that in normal life too. When you are preparing a dish, you always taste it before serves it to your guests. You want to be sure, that the dish is delicious before you show it. The same should be with applications. First we test application, then we show it to the users.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">4Developers Wroclaw - 2019</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/4developers-wroclaw-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4Developers Wroclaw - 2019" /><published>2020-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/4developers-wroclaw-2019</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="4Developers" /><summary type="html">In 2019 I had an opportunity to be a speaker and participant on three local 4Deveopers events. In Krakow and in Katowice I was presenting my two speeches. I wrote about them an article Speaker at 4Developers 2019. One of my presentations you can watch on YouTube: Are you an Egoistic Programmer? - Step by step refactoring. The last event was in Wroclaw. This time I was a participant. It was a nice feeling to be there only as a participant. I could focus on conference its self without stressing out. How in few words I can describe 4Developers in Wroclaw? Presentations, discussion with people and a little bit of fun. </summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Occupational burnout syndrome</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/occupational-burnout" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Occupational burnout syndrome" /><published>2019-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/occupational-burnout</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="career" /><category term="health" /><summary type="html">Today very important, health related topic. Did you ever feel exhaustion, negativity, cynicism or lack of energy related to your job for a long period of time? Or maybe you have headaches, problems with sleeping, chest pain, a feeling of breathlessness or anger. This all symptoms can be related with occupational burnout syndrome. Read this article to get more information about burnout syndrome before it will affect your health, relations and life.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Rails Girls Warsaw (19 - 20 October 2019)</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/rails-girls-warsaw-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rails Girls Warsaw (19 - 20 October 2019)" /><published>2019-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/rails-girls-warsaw-2019</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="Rails Girls" /><category term="Ruby on Rails" /><summary type="html">There it is! The Rails Girls Warsaw 2019 edition! Rails Girls workshops in Warsaw are one of my favorites in Poland. They are always close to my heart. First time I was a mentor at Rails Girls Warsaw in 2014. Now I go around Poland to share my programming knowledge. This time in Warsaw.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Local editions of 4Developers 2019</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/4developers-local-events-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Local editions of 4Developers 2019" /><published>2019-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/4developers-local-events-2019</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="4Developers" /><summary type="html">In one of my last articles I have written about my new challenge. To be a speaker at a conference. This happened two times at local editions of 4Developers in Krakow and in Katowice. It was for me interesting experience, especially that this audience doesn’t know Ruby as programming language too well. I had a chance to share my knowledge about Ruby and good programming practices with them. In the near future there are going to be two more local editions of 4Developers. And because of that I have a surprise for you which is prepared together with 4Developers organizers. I have for you a discount for these two events and one free ticket which you can win. But let’s start from the beginning.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Iterators in Ruby</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/ruby-iterators" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Iterators in Ruby" /><published>2019-10-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/ruby-iterators</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="Ruby" /><summary type="html">Ruby as other programming languages has many ways to repeat instructions. We can use loops for that. Loops like loop, while, until or even for. This is very useful, but Ruby has also something like iterators. Iterators are even more awesome than loops. In Ruby you have many iterators with some specific destiny. You can use each, map, collect, select, find, times or even more. But wait! When should I choose each and when should I choose map? This is a good question! And I’m going to answer it.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">4Developers 2019</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/4developers-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4Developers 2019" /><published>2019-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/4developers-2019</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="4Developers" /><summary type="html">Normally I’m quite active in Rails Girls community. I’m a mentor and an organizer, and also a speaker at Rails Girls workshops. In this year is a little bit different. I spend less time supporting Rails Girls events, but I challenged myself in a different way. I started sending my proposals to the conferences. I wanted to be a speaker at more than just local community groups or Rails Girls events.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Functional programming in Ruby</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/functional-programming-ruby" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Functional programming in Ruby" /><published>2019-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/functional-programming-ruby</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="Ruby" /><summary type="html">Ruby is an object oriented language. That doesn’t mean we cannot do some functional programming in Ruby. When you take a look closer to the history of the Ruby language, you can find out, that Ruby was influenced by other languages like Perl, Smalltalk, Eiffel, Ada, Basic or Lisp. Because of this different inspirations we can find in Ruby not only object oriented concepts, but also a little bit of functional programming.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Ruby pattern matching</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/ruby-pattern-matching" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ruby pattern matching" /><published>2019-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/ruby-pattern-matching</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="Ruby" /><summary type="html">Some time ago I wrote an article about Pattern matching in Elixir. I really like this idea. Now from Ruby version 2.7 we have pattern matching in Ruby!!! It is not the same like in Elixir, but it is a nice feature to have. Keep in mind that this is still an experimental feature, so it can change in the future versions of Ruby. Let’s check out what we can do with pattern matching in Ruby.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">How to become a programmer?</title><link href="https://womanonrails.com/where-to-start" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to become a programmer?" /><published>2019-05-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://womanonrails.com/where-to-start</id><author><name>womanonrails</name></author><category term="career" /><summary type="html">I’ve been working in the programming world since 2011. Before then, I spent about 6 years searching my own life path. When I was starting this adventure, my goal was completely different. I wanted to be a math teacher. During those 6 years, in most cases, I didn’t know what I was doing. Where should I spent my time? On what should I focus? I studied hard, but to be honest, I didn’t know where all this will end. Especially when some of my plans failed. I put more details about my journey in about me section, check it out if you want to know more about me. Right now I’m programmer and I teach people what I already know. I share my knowledge in many different ways. I do workshops for women like Rails Girls. I teach children on CoderDojo. I write Woman On Rails blog. I met lots of people who want to change their life. They want to be programmers or testers or even start something which need more programming skills. I’m helping them change their career path. And I’m proud of them, because this change is hard and need some sacrifices. During that process, I get lots of questions about How to start in programming? Today I would like to answer those questions in public.</summary></entry></feed>